The following content is provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare at
ocw.mit.edu.
And I think we're about ready to get started.
So welcome, folks, for lecture number two of Fundamentals
Affordable Takes, focused on the solar resource.
What I wanted to do to get everybody in the mood of
thinking about the sun is pass around a few balls.
So this is really A, to limber you all up.
But B, whoops, there we go.
All right, don't let it fall.
There you go.
I know Ashley's got solid hands.
All right, here's one.
Pass that around as well.
Get a few more.
There, there.
And lastly, right up the middle.
There you go.
OK, so today's lecture is really about the solar resource.
And as we go through, it kind of helps to have a sphere in
your hand, since oftentimes we perceive the world as being
flat, no fault of our own.
Locally, one can approximate it as a flat body.
That's certainly a good possibility.
Wouldn't mind passing these out to your friends as well.
Thanks.
But in reality, if we really want to understand the solar
resource, we really have to begin understanding or
thinking in terms of spheres and in terms of circles or, in
most cases, ellipses.
And so we're going to dive into the solar resource.
Before we really dive in in detail into the solar resource,
I wanted to give you feedback to your surveys.
So you did a background assessment survey, a census,
if you will, and filled out a number of questions last
class about your backgrounds.
And I wanted to provide you the feedback, the consolidated
information, because it's really telling about who your
colleagues are.
This right here is a little bit of a snapshot of expertise
and current career trajectory.
So the self-defined expertise on the bottom left is really, I
think, the most telling parameter.
For the undergrads here, you may define yourself by your
major today.
But when you graduate and go on to grad school, you might
say, for example, do your undergrad in physics and then
do your graduate school in mechanical engineering, but
still consider yourself a physicist at heart.
And so that's why I ask this question here.
What is your self-defined expertise, because there are
several graduate students who have changed fields, if you
will, from undergrad to graduate school?
Most people in the audience, by and large, consider
themselves engineers, either material science engineers or
mechanical engineers.
Chemistry is strong as well.
And then we have about 10 different departments here
represented.
And that's really cool.
It's going to manifest itself in the class projects.
And you'll see the diversity of different inputs and
perspectives from your colleagues.
The degree in progress, undergrad, grad is about
split 1 third, 2 thirds, undergrad and grad.
ASP is Advanced Studies Program.
So these are folks coming in from industry who are actually
here in the classroom.
Some of your colleagues in the class are folks who are in
industry and perhaps have real-world PV experience.
Several of the people here in the class as well have
gained expertise in solar with their hobbies, with their
work, some have installed solar panels, other ones have
done research or are doing research in solar.
So it's a pretty diverse group.
And some are as well members of the solar car team, which is
rolling out its new model a few days time.
In terms of learning methods, it was pretty well split between
hands-on labs, field trips, and guest lectures.
And I'll get back to that in a few slides.
In terms of class project interest, there was a strong
interest in working with pre-established projects.
So we've listened to that.
This is pretty consistent with previous years.
And so we have several pre-prepared class projects
ready for you.
And a few of you had an interest in the self-designed
project.
I'd like to talk to you.
I'd like to begin developing those ideas as soon as
possible so that when we start assembling teams, if you do
have a strong idea for a class project, we can begin
crafting that and molding that starting now.
So please come up and have a chat with me after class or
during office hours or during recitation.
These are your learning objectives defined by you.
And they range, I tried to give it some continuum
spectrum from natural sciences to social sciences and
engineering in the middle.
And obviously, this is more of a loop than a linear line.
But bear with me.
There was a strong interest in fundamentals.
And that's certainly, I think, what the core of the class
is about, at least the first third of the class.
Going in terms of size of the bubble, these are the number
of people who listed a particular topic as a great
interest to them.
Economics and market, systems and grid, current
technologies, emerging technologies.
And so listening to all of this, we are in the process of
preparing for you some guest lectures and field trips based
on this feedback right here.
We have already lined up a field trip to a local PV
research laboratory that produces modules like this one
right here, only much, much bigger, and has strong
collaboration with existing companies, startup companies
in the area, as well as more established companies.
So that'll be a lot of fun.
And we're currently in the process of arranging other
field trips and guest lectures to match this
feedback right here.
So thank you.
We'll mold the course, shape it, craft it to
fit your interests.
So to hop into the solar resource, and without further
do, the subject of today, and the motivation for wearing
this tie, is really the solar resource, the sun.
This is where it all starts.
If we're to understand PV photovoltaics, the conversion
of sunlight into electricity, it starts from the sun.
And so spending some good time thinking about the sun is
really, really important.
And it will avoid the embarrassing situation.
How many of you have been at a shopping center, walking
along, and a little child is asking his parent, dad, why
is the sky blue, or why is the such and such?
And the answer is you'll hear just make you want to tear
your ears out, and say, my goodness.
So part of this is just general knowledge, it's getting
a feel for the world and the universe, and asking those
questions again that the little children will ask, but that
we forget to ask as we move on with our lives, right?
OK, so moving forward, the learning objectives for today
are these right here.
By the end of the lecture, and hopefully you already have a
good sense of this based on your readings already, and I'll
quiz you on that in a second, verbally, we want to be able to
quantify the available solar resource relative to human
energy needs and other fuel sources.
We want to recognize and plot air mass 0 and air mass 1.5
solar spectra, and describe the physical origins.
We want to describe how a solar insulation maps, these are
solar resource maps, in other words, how much sunlight is
available.
And we want to be able to estimate a solar resource
amount locally at a specific spot on the planet.
We want to list the causes of variation and intermittency of
the solar resource, and quantify their time constant and
magnitude.
In other words, we want to be able to discern what are the
big effects and what are the ones that don't really matter.
We want to be able to estimate the land area needed to provide
sufficient solar resource for a project, whether it's a house,
a car, a village, a country, a world.
And a lot of this will be on your homework assignment.
So we'll give you the tools here, but then ask you to
address those questions.
And for those of you who have already picked up your piece
at number one, you'll see relevant questions.
Where's this?
Did anybody recognize this right here?
I start rambling off names.
What city has Pennsylvania Avenue, Independence Ave,
Washington, DC?
This is right outside of the National Air and Space Museum.
What this little girl here is pointing to is the sun.
And then we have Mercury, Venus, Earth, Mars, and so forth.
So it's essentially a solar system to scale.
As you walk out of the Air and Space Museum and walk down
the street, you'll be passing the different bodies in our
solar system.
And so just as a quick little review to kind of get us
situated and to ask the questions that little kiddies
might ask us, how far is it from the earth to the sun?
About 100 million miles, yeah, 93 million miles.
Less or minus somewhere in the range of maybe a percent or
so, a few percent, depending on what time of year we are,
since we're in a little bit of an elliptical orbit.
Good, so that's the distance to the sun.
It'd be about 150 million kilometers.
How long does it take light to travel that distance?
About eight minutes, eight and a third minutes, right?
So it takes a little bit for the light to reach us.
Good, some more questions.
How far are the other planets in our solar system to the sun?
Just going in order from Mercury out.
It's to get us situated here.
If we are at any point planning and throwing up
satellites and sending them to other planets, this is a good
thing to kind of keep in the back of our minds.
So if we define an astronomical unit, not in terms of our
national debt, but in terms of the distance from the earth to
the sun, that's an astronomical unit.
Mercury would be somewhere around 0.4, Venus 0.7, Mars 1.5.
So that's all kind of in our neighborhood, right?
And then from Mars to Jupiter, there's a bit of a jump.
It goes from 1.5 to 5.
Then from Jupiter to Saturn, it's 10.
Well, sorry, 10 is the distance from Saturn to the sun.
And then 30 and then 40.
Sorry, 10, 20, 30, 40.
So it goes, Jupiter is 5.
Saturn 10, Uranus would be 20.
Neptune 30, Pluto 40.
Pluto, planet, sort of.
So it's easy to remember those numbers, because it goes
5, 10, 20.
That's just essentially a sequence of doubling.
And then 10, 20, 30, 40.
I'm giving you approximate numbers here, but that's
something just to keep in mind, all in terms of
astronomical units.
So in case a little kid comes up and asks you, you can spread
out the answer.
Let's talk about the sun.
This is just a review of our readings right here.
This was a representation of the sun and the earth
moving around.
And what is solstice and equinox?
What do those refer to?
What is the equinox?
Equinox of light and dark.
Yeah, equal amount of light and dark throughout pretty much
all the world, except if you're really standing on the
tippy top in the bottom.
So equal amount of light and dark throughout the world on
that particular day.
So the day and the night have the same amount of length.
If you move over into this region right here, this would
be a region of our northern hemisphere summer, southern
hemisphere winter, over here, vice versa.
And the solstice would be the shortest or the longest day of
the year, depending on what side you're on.
So in the northern hemisphere, the June solstice would be the
summer solstice for us.
It would be the longest day.
And if you're in the southern hemisphere, it would be the
shortest day.
Depending on what time zone you're in, there might be a
variation of one day hither or two.
Good.
And what are the seasons caused by?
What is this kind of tilt right here?
What is that called?
Declination angle.
And approximately how much is that?
23.45.
So 23 and 1 half degrees.
Good.
And we can visualize all of this on the PVCD ROM, on the
website.
So this was part of your signed reading.
And here's the earth going around the sun in this
representation.
Likewise, if you want to take one of your balls and just
kind of imagine being on one of those surfaces, you see the
diurnal rotation here.
It's spinning around its axis and as well the seasonal
variation as it spins around the sun.
That's important for a number of reasons.
That will determine how much sunlight is normally
incident on the planet.
If you are normally incident, if you're at this exact spot
right here, you're receiving the sunlight full on.
But if you're up here somewhere, your surface normal is
pointing, some vector pointing out like that, you're only
going to be receiving the cosine theta of that amount of
sun.
So if you're in extreme example, if you're right here,
you're not going to get any.
But if you're in this part right here, you're going to
get cosine of 0, which would be 1.
So you get the full amount of sun.
And likewise, as you move through the angles here.
So it's important to understand what the relative
angle is between our surface normal and the vector
pointing at the sun.
That varies as a function of season.
It varies as a function of time of day.
And obviously over the entire earth, you can define the
precise amount of sunlight coming in, the precise solar
resource by a series of trig formulae.
It gets pretty complex.
And this website will actually walk you through it, if
you're so interested.
Now, this is all review, since folks have all done the
background reading, right?
All done the background reading.
Expect you to before class.
Let me ask you a few trickier questions just to see if our
creative juices are really moving at this early time of
day.
When would be the shortest day of the year?
Let's start there.
The shortest day of the year is approximately December 22nd
in the salsas.
When is the latest sunrise?
And when is the earliest sunset?
You might need to pick up your little ball and rotate it
around.
Does anybody have a, even just a gut sense, would it be on
the salsas?
How many people think it's going to be exactly on the
salsas?
Let's see, earliest sunset.
How many people think that the earliest sunset's going to be
a little bit before the salsas?
How many people think a little bit after the salsas?
I know people don't really know.
The reality is that the earliest sunset would be a
little bit before the salsas here, and the latest sunrise
would be a little bit after the salsas.
And it flips in summertime.
It would be, let's see, the earliest sunrise and the
latest sunset before and after the salsas, respectively.
And you can kind of think about that in terms of what is the
solar noon?
The solar noon is when the sun is directly overhead relative
to our chronological noon, which is, I would say, less
dependent on the specific angle of the Earth relative to the
sun as it moves around this trajectory.
Let's get more into that in recitation.
I sense since there wasn't much traction there, I don't
want to dwell.
OK.
Good, good, good.
Let's think a little bit more in terms of the trajectory of
the sun later on as we move through some of the
introductory material.
I don't want to dwell too much.
I want to give a little bit of review since I'm sensing that
not everybody did the readings.
I expect you to do the readings, folks.
So let's keep with me here.
So a touch of history.
Since that was requested, I decided to launch a little bit
into a history of the study of the sun.
Philosophers, going back to what I suppose most would
consider early India, studied the sun.
There were some writings of some of the earlier
philosophers that were recorded.
Some have interpreted these writings as being indicative of
perhaps heliocentric models.
These are poetry, folks.
It's a very different style of communication than what we
have today of technical writing.
So it's difficult for us to discern, or difficult for me
at least to discern when I read the lines verbatim, if
this is really somebody thinking about the heliocentric
model, or whether this is somebody just describing the
universe and the best of their abilities.
The real beginnings of heliocentric models began in
the third century before the Common Era.
And the notions of interstellar distances
estimated in a similar manner to what we just walked
through today.
Estimating the distance between the earth and the sun, and
then using that as a measure, or a yardstick, with which to
measure the distances to the other planets began somewhere
during that time.
Likewise, these writings of old made their way to the
Middle East.
And in the 10th and 11th centuries of the Common Era,
the Middle East, the Arab world was really where science
and technology was at.
And these days, Europe was still largely mild in the
Middle Ages, starting to emerge in a few places.
But by and large, the carriers of civilization in the Western
world were really centered in some of the Arab
cities in the Middle East.
And al-Biruni in particular was very avid at applying
methods of astronomical observation, in
particular to aid travel, but in the process discovering a
thing or two about our known universe.
And of course, finally, Johannes Kepler in Europe,
once it starts to emerge from the Middle Ages, with really
taking observations from other scientists who very
carefully plotted out the position of the different
bodies, he came up with some of the mathematical models that
described the motion of the planets through the skies, and
is largely credited with developing a series of laws
that define interplanetary motion.
So a couple of interesting things to note is that
international collaboration was really essential.
These ideas didn't develop in isolation.
They were flowing throughout the world.
It's important to know that many of the scientists were
well-traveled polyglots, meaning they spoke different
languages, and that's how they were able to interpret the
texts and readings of other people.
And it's also to note that parallel astronomical
developments were happening in other regions of the world,
the Far East, Mesoamerica, and so forth.
And so obviously there may have been some communication, I
would say rather sparse, especially with the Far East.
But there was a fair amount of communication between these
regions here, and you can imagine writings or ideas
traveling from word of mouth along trade routes.
So there was some communication.
So back to our learning objectives.
Today we're about to quantify the available solar resource
relative to human energies and other fuel sources.
So let's do that.
We'll jump right into one of the slides I
showed you last time.
This is in terms of TerraWatts Ave.
TerraWatts is a unit of power, a very big one.
Terra is 10 to the 12.
And you can see here the resource of the sun relative to
the wind energy resource space relative to human energy
needs.
If we just consider the resource falling on the Earth's
surface as opposed to that falling in the outer atmosphere,
there's a little bit of a discount, but we're still very
large compared to human energy use.
And if we redefine our units from TerraWatts into HECs,
which are human energy consumptions defined in, say,
2050, where one HEC is the average, let's say, energy
burn rate of 2050, you can see here that these numbers are
a few orders of magnitude larger than what our human
energy needs are.
So if you were able to capture only 1% of all of the solar
resource falling on the Earth's crust, we would be
actually in pretty good shape.
And 1% of the total land area on the Earth's crust, I
believe somewhere between 1% and 2% of the United States is
covered in asphalt right now for roads.
So this could be on houses, on rooftops, on buildings, and
so forth.
We wouldn't necessarily have to exclusively repave virgin
farmland with solar panels.
So going back to quantifying the solar power, we have our
sun.
We're going to start by quantifying the solar resource
by assuming that the sun is a black body.
The same way that hot objects emit light, say, for example,
when you turn up your stove and you have a very warm glow
coming out of it, the sun is as well a hot body, a black
body, sorry, very hot as well.
Somewhere around 6,000 Kelvin.
And the total radiated power is given by Stefan
Boltzmann's law here in the following way, where we have
temperature to the fourth and the temperature is somewhere
around 6,000 Kelvin.
And so we have this power being radiated out at the surface
of the sun.
And then as it travels outward, it becomes, you could say,
diluted in effect, because the total surface area of that
sphere is increasing, obviously, as r squared.
And so by the time that that light reaches the earth, it's
only a very small cross-section, or very small solid
angle, to be more precise, of the sun's surface that is
radiating directly at the earth right here, because this in
the absence of scattering centers in the universe that
might reflect or bounce the light back toward the earth.
And you can calculate the total power incident on the earth
by that simple formula right there.
What is the radius of the earth?
Again, one of these simple numbers you should kind of
have in your head, 6,370 kilometers,
somewhere in that order.
And so you can begin estimating here the total power
and the order of magnitude.
It's going to be tiny compared to the total power that the sun
is radiating, thankfully, or else we'd be
pretty hot right now.
So the average power coming from the sun on the surface of
the outer atmosphere is around 1366 watts per square meter.
Who's heard of 1366 before?
Yeah, you've heard about it?
All right, you know where the number comes from now.
It's pretty wonky.
1366 is a startup company, a spin-off of MIT,
focused on solar energy.
OK, and so that's at the equinox, which we just learned
is occurring somewhere around March 21, September 21,
coming up soon, celebration.
The ratio of the surface areas of the spheres is really
something to keep in mind right there.
OK, so we've quantified the available resource relative
to human energy needs.
Now we have to come up with some language that we use to
describe the sunlight moving through the atmosphere of the
Earth and reaching the surface of the Earth, right?
So we're going to use what's called the air mass convention,
or AM convention.
AM stands for air mass.
Even without knowing much about how the light is absorbed
or how to quantify it mathematically, we can assume
that our atmosphere contains molecules, it contains
particulate matter, and that's going to interact with the
light in some ways.
Probably going to either absorb or scatter it.
And so as the light passes through our atmosphere, there's
going to be some absorption.
And the greater the distance, the greater the optical
path length through the atmosphere, the more absorption
and more scattering there will be.
And so we use air mass, or AM convention, to define the
path length or the path distance through the atmosphere.
AM0 would mean the outer atmosphere.
AM1 would be essentially just going straight through,
normal incidence, so that the direction of the trajectory
of the light is parallel to the surface normal of the
Earth at that location.
And then air mass 1.5 and so forth is as we increase the
angle of the entry of light relative to the surface normal.
So in other words, as we go further from the equator to
northern latitudes, that air mass number is
going to go up, up, up.
OK, we'll explain it with a few graphs and figures and a few
slides.
So we have our atmospheric absorption.
When you just glance at the Earth and these beautiful
pictures taken from outer space, we can see very
obviously the clouds present.
And more importantly, if we were to zoom in on one of
these regions right here, we would see this blueish hue
coming from our atmosphere, which is scattering
preferentially the shorter wavelengths of light.
And more importantly, this radius right here is somewhere
in the order of 6,370 kilometers.
And this thin atmospheric shell is in the order of 30.
So that's why you don't really see too much of a ring
around the planet from this distance.
So atmospheric effects.
Let's try to bin them into discrete buckets.
This is a simplification, but it helps us gain a foothold
in understanding.
And then from there, we can make our understanding a bit
more complex.
So we have incoming solar radiation coming from here.
We have a number now that's 342 watts per square meter.
Why is that number so much lower than the 1366 that we
were just talking about?
OK.
Yeah, so this is meant to be an average over the entire day.
One fixed point along the ground, right?
So as we're rotating around, we have at least half of the day
normally when we don't have sunlight.
And then there's, let's say, the cosine theta angle is not
one at all times.
It's very rarely one.
And so this is a bit of a discounted incoming solar
radiation, essentially a time average solar radiation for
a given patch of the planet over a typical day.
And so we have a variety of processes here.
We have reflection off of clouds.
That's pretty clear to see from here.
Looks nice and white.
We have some absorbed by the atmosphere, typically in
rotational or vibrational modes of molecules up in the
outer atmosphere, sometimes by particulate matter as well.
And then we have the amount that is absorbed here by the
surface, of course, reflected as well.
And so the amount that's incident on the surface or
coming down to us is what we can actually use to
make solar energy.
And this is an average, right?
Because sometimes the cloud cover is a lot greater.
And for that particular day, we will have a lot less
resource striking the ground at a given time.
This over here, this is all mostly infrared, right?
Where this is visible coming in once the light gets absorbed
and then gets re-emitted, usually gets re-emitted in
a longer wavelength light, or the infrared light.
And this is the stuff that gets absorbed by greenhouse
gases and then re-emitted equiangularly, and some of
it makes its way back to the Earth.
OK, so air mass.
Let's define that so that we have a common language that we
can use to describe the solar resource from place to place.
So again, this is the sun.
This is the surface right here.
And let's imagine that the angle between the incident
sunlight and the surface normal is 0, such that the
cosine theta term is 1.
Air mass here at this point on the surface of the Earth is
going to be AM1.
So we call it air mass 1 if the sun is literally directly
overhead.
What did we learn about the declination angle of the
Earth?
It's about 23 and a half degrees, right?
How far north are we?
What is our latitude here in Boston?
41, 42-ish, right?
So let's, for simplicity, say that here in Boston, our
latitude of Boston Logan Airport is approximately 41
degrees north.
And let's say that the declination of our planet
is approximately 23 and a half degrees.
So what would be the angle of the sun in the sky if you were
to lie on your back in the middle of the summer
solstice and the middle of the winter solstice, and you're
lying straight on your back looking up at solar noon, what
would the angle of the sun in the sky be relative to the
surface normal?
How far south would the sun be?
Imagine that this is 0 degrees and that's 90, right?
So relative to this angle right here, where would the sun be
in the sky?
Why don't you turn to your neighbor right now and
discuss on the summer solstice, the winter solstice.
Come up with some set of angles there.
All right, folks, what did we come up with?
This is our little human being, you, in Boston.
This is south, and that's north.
And we're at the solar noon in the winter solstice and the
summer solstice.
So here's you.
This is directly above.
So let's say if you're lying on your back and looking
straight up, that's the surface normal of the earth.
In the summer at solar noon, the sun would be at what angle
relative to the surface normal of the earth?
17 and 1 half somewhere around there.
And how did you get that number?
Subtract those two, right?
So you get 41 minus 23 and 1 half.
You're somewhere around 17, 18 somewhere around there.
So we'll call it 18 degrees in summer, again, relative to
the surface normal.
And in winter time, what does that work out to be?
64 and 1 half, similar logic, right?
So we'll call it 65 degrees in winter.
Good.
So what does that work out to be in terms of air mass for
winter and summer?
Quick engineering approximation, I'm going to say that
in summer it's approximately air mass one, but you can
calculate it real quick.
Somebody with a calculator want to plug those in?
And roughly two in winter, right?
OK.
We're going to get into scattering of light in next
lecture, actually.
And we'll see why that matters in terms, especially of
getting sunburned, since the shorter wavelengths, the
ultraviolet, are more sensitive to the path length.
OK.
Good.
Very good.
So we have pretty much a gut sense now of where the sun
is in the sky.
And as it moves from summer to winter, from our perspective,
it follows a little bit of a sinusoidal path, right?
It stays in summer for a long period of time up here.
And then it moves pretty quickly down here and stays here.
So versus time, the angle of the sun in the sky is
following a sine curve, or a cosine curve, if you will.
And so right now, the sun is actually close to the middle.
We're in September 13.
The solstice is coming up in a week's time.
And so the slope of that sine curve is at a maximum, right
about now.
And so the amount of time that the day will change in length
is changing at its greatest point right now in the year.
And so you really begin to notice it if you start
paying attention.
Or if you go to weather.com and start looking up how long is
today's day going to last?
When is the sunset tomorrow?
I don't know about you folks, but I like to cycle.
And when I'm doing my evening rides, I'm noticing it now
that I have to start earlier and earlier if I want to put in,
say, 30 or 40 miles.
I'm not going to be able to make it home in time.
So that's the sun and how it relates to you in your daily
lives.
We're going to get back to this in a minute.
So keep this in mind.
Don't let it out of your ram.
Let's talk about the actual solar spectrum for a minute.
This is the sunlight intensity in some very weird units.
We'll get to that in a minute.
But think of this in terms sort of like the total amount of
power in a given bandwidth.
So the wavelength right here, the power density in a bandwidth,
the wavelength is the wavelength of light.
Shown for your convenience here is the visible spectrum.
That's mostly what our eye is able to detect in this wavelength
range right here.
And the sun is emitting over a much broader range of wavelengths.
It's emitting following a black body emission source at 6,000
Kelvin.
And that's in this very difficult to see green line
right there.
Airmass zero spectrum looks like this, this red line right
here.
And again, let me remind you that the air mass zero is the
light that's falling in the outer atmosphere.
There is no Earth atmospheric absorption net.
Why do we have these little lines here?
You see it's not a perfect black body.
We have some, I'll give you a hint, absorption lines.
Where is that light being absorbed?
Is it the ether between the Earth and the sun?
No, it's no ether between the Earth and the sun.
Where is that light being absorbed?
Hydrogen ions.
In the sun itself, right?
So these are absorption events occurring in the solar
atmosphere.
And now if we do air mass one or 1.5, let's push it up a
little bit from air mass zero, this is now passing through an
angle somewhere around 60 degrees.
Now what do we have?
We have several absorption lines occurring, right?
And these correspond to absorption events where?
In the Earth's atmosphere.
Exactly.
And so we can attribute each of these little absorption
lines here to a particular, usually it's a molecule, in
the Earth's atmosphere.
Note the sensitivity of the human eye in black right here
and how well matched it is to the air mass 1.5 spectrum.
That's pretty cool.
OK, so there you have the spectrum.
Let's get to these units of power density per bandwidth
for a second.
The way to think about those units is as follows.
Kilowatts per meter squared, OK, get that.
It's the amount of power falling on the unit area.
Per micron, the reason it's normalized per micron is
because the wavelength units right here is in microns.
And if you take the product of the two, it makes it pretty
easy to calculate the total power density.
So if you want to calculate the power density, the total
watts per square meter falling on the Earth, say between 0.5
and 1 micron, you can calculate the total amount of
power by multiplying one versus the other.
So that's why they're in this weird unit right here.
It's to help you perform calculations, like the ones
you'll do in your homework, like the ones you'll do for
your class project, and so forth.
And it strikes a little bit odd the first time you look at
it, but it begins making sense.
And you're appreciative of it after a while.
There are standard spectra.
They're standard reference spectra.
Sure, you can go outside and using some form of a
spectrophotometer.
You can measure the incident solar radiation and map out
the spectral irradiance as a function of wavelength.
In terms of planning or communicating with other
scientists, we typically refer to standards.
We use common yardsticks, common metrics, and that
facilitates communication, avoids ambiguity, avoids
misunderstanding.
And so these standards right here, these ASTMs, refer to
the particular standards that are used for those solar
spectra.
And then you're supporting online material at the very
end of the lecture slides online.
We go into some more detail regarding that for those who
are interested.
So again, these little absorption lines here correspond
to specific atmospheric events, interactions of that
particular wavelength of light, with some molecule
usually in the atmosphere.
We can as well have generalized attenuation due to other
scattering mechanisms.
Notice right here in the short wavelengths what's
happening.
From the red to the blue, this light is particularly
affected.
We have a sharp drop in the shorter wavelengths, and it
grows sharper the shorter in wavelength you go.
So the attenuation, due to passing through the atmosphere,
grows or increases the shorter in wavelength you go.
And this is a process generally called Rayleigh
scattering.
And there is a wavelength to the fourth dependence.
So as you go shorter and shorter in wavelength, the
likelihood or probability of scattering will increase.
Why is that pertinent to us?
Well, now you can answer that little child who walks up to
you in the shopping mall and says, why is the sky blue?
You say, well, there is this elastic scattering mechanism
of electromagnetic radiation whereby in a broad spectral
event, such as a sun, black body emission, we have the
shorter wavelengths that are scattered more.
And that's why when we look away from the sun in the other
direction, we see those shorter wavelengths that are
scattered back to us.
That is pertinent for two reasons.
A, it makes the sky look blue.
Secondly, it's not only the short wavelengths in blue
light that we're worried about, but also the ultraviolet
radiation.
So even on a cloudy day, if there is a few open patches
and you can get a scattered light coming in, you can still
get sunburn.
And secondly, there is a very strong dependence on the
path length, the optical path length, the air mass.
So if you go further north in latitudes, where your air mass
increases, because now, if you think about the atmosphere as
being kind of a flat, just give me
approximation for a minute, if you think of the earth being
flat and the atmosphere being flat, now the path length in
winter is much, much greater than the path length in
summer.
Same sun, just different path length, much more likely to
get sunburn in summer than you are in winter.
Because the path length is a lot shorter and the amount of
short wavelength ultraviolet radiation that will be scattered
away is going to be less in the summer than in winter.
That's also why if you go south in latitude, for example,
from here, say, to Miami, your incidence of getting sunburn is
a lot greater, a lot more than the total increase of the
visible portion of the spectrum.
So the sun might not look that different to you, but your
incidence of sunburn events goes up quite a bit.
And that is due to Rayleigh scattering.
And now, by this point, the little child has already run
crying back to the parent.
But you have a full satisfaction of knowing how the
universe around you is put together.
And that actually was a pretty deep problem.
It took a long time for at least European scientists to
crack that nut and figure out what was going on.
Describe how solar installation maps are made and use them to
estimate the local solar resource.
So we have metrology.
We have techniques that we can use to measure the amount of
sunlight that is out there.
And now we want to apply those in some systematic fashion to
measure the average solar resource around the planet,
including the oceans, and then use that information to
estimate, later on, the land area needed or the size of the
array or how many cells we're going to have to string
together based on the solar resource locally.
So how are these insulation maps made, these maps that we'll
use as engineers to size our systems?
First off, let me define insulation.
This is not insulation, as in stuff you put around the house
to keep the heat from going out.
This is insulation with an O, a shorthand for incoming solar
radiation, insulation at the top there.
It's typically given in units of energy per unit area per
unit time.
So kilowatt hours, that's energy, per meter squared per
day.
And it's helpful when designing or projecting these PV
systems.
And it's affected by a bunch of stuff, which we'll get to
over the next few slides.
So we can measure insulation from the ground.
That's a surefire way to do it.
This right here is a pyrenometer.
Pyro, fire, sun, anode on top of.
So anode, cathode, cata, under, ana, above,
catatonic, under.
So pyrenometer.
So it's basically measuring the sun above, measuring the
sunlight above.
This is a full hemisphere, measuring the sunlight coming
in from all angles.
There's a small little sensor right here.
It's lying flat.
And that glasses essentially allowing the light from
different angles to get into the sensor.
And this is a very narrow, solid angle of the sky.
It's probably just looking at the sun, or in a particular
direction, rather, plus or minus 2 and 1 half degrees in
either direction.
So it's a very limited, solid angle of the sky.
This one over here would be more appropriate, say, for a
flat panel that's receiving scattered light coming in at
all angles.
This one over here would be more appropriate for a
tracking system, especially a concentrator system that's
has optics that only accept light in from a very limited
solid angle.
So imagine you have a lens that has to have light incident
to it to focus it on the right spot.
And if the sun moves in the wrong spot, or put it another
way, if the lens is in the wrong position relative to the
incident solar radiation, the light is being focused off of
the solar cell, and it doesn't produce any power.
So this is a system that's used for measuring the direct
solar spectrum, which will be useful for calculating the
total output from concentrator systems.
And this pyrometer over here is useful for
flat panel systems.
And we can also measure the total amount of incident
solar radiation, total amount of insulation from the sky
using satellite imagery.
This is an example of a measurement.
And this right here is insulation, average insulation,
from 0 to 550 watts per square meter taken from a NASA
satellite with the NASA Earth Observatory.
Very cool website, great place to spend a Friday night if
you've done the plans.
Just log on here and bunches of maps from snow cover to
population density to CO2 being emitted to wildfires
around the planet.
Anything that a satellite can measure, they're measuring.
And the insulation value is one of them.
And so we have data from various points.
This is the insulation in January.
So in January, it's the southern hemisphere's summer,
the northern hemisphere's winter.
And as a result, we have less insulation up north.
We're in the blues.
And the southern hemisphere is more in the reds.
And of course, the tide turns.
In July, we have our summer.
And the southern hemisphere has their winter.
And the poor folks here in Antarctica have nothing.
So a couple of things to note, just already straight off
the bat, we're noticing that there's, in general, higher
insulation near the equator.
The equator passing right through here, approximately.
Fun fact, small city up there in the north of Brazil.
There's a soccer field that is half in the north and half
in the south.
That's neither here nor there.
We have rainforests up here in the north of Brazil, central
Africa, and here in Southeast Asia.
And even when the sun is directly overhead, those
clouds are preventing some of the sunlight from getting in.
And that's why right at the equator itself, we typically
have less insulation than we do in the tropics, say,
tropic of capricorn, tropic of cancer,
tropic of capricorn running straight through
Sao Paulo, Brazil, tropic of cancer
running through Key West, just to situate yourselves.
And the tropics are how far away from the equator?
OK, 23 and a half.
Good guess.
Good.
So what we're going to do is now launch into our next
learning objective, which is to list the causes of variation
and intermittency of the solar resource and quantify the time
constants and magnitudes.
This is really, really, really, really important.
The other stuff is very useful from an engineering point of
view, from answering certain questions in your homework.
This right here determines, or is one of the singular reasons
why solar doesn't behave like a regular fossil fuel source.
Why solar does not produce power all the time.
It is variable in terms of its power output.
Variability generally refers to the fact that we can predict
it's coming.
It's going to vary, but at least we can predict it's coming.
Intermittency, while not a strict definition, the
understanding when somebody says intermittency or
intermittent power source, the impression that it gives is
that it's unpredictable in terms of its variability in
its variation.
So we've talked a little bit about the variation so far and
about the predictable nature of the sun.
We've talked about how the sunlight, the solar resource,
varies from summer to winter.
We've talked about how the solar resource varies as a
function of latitude.
But now we're going to talk not only in a little bit more
depth about that and have a few fun in class exercises to
get us really grasping that concept in its entirety, but
also talk about some sources of intermittency, which if you
have a large amount of solar contributing to the grid and it
is intermittent and you have no way of dealing with that,
you're going to have fluctuations of energy
level on the grid, or power levels, here as a function of
time, and that's not going to be good.
So in terms of the seasonal variations, in terms of
predicting the amount coming from the sun at a given point,
I told you it looked a little bit like a sine or cosine
wave, and indeed it does.
You can calculate those values based on this website right
here, just to show you how nifty and cool it is.
Our friends at Arizona State University, Stuart Bowden and
Christiana Hansberg, really put in a lot of time to make this.
You can vary the time or the day of year, right here, for
instance, and you can see how the solar resource, this is the
direct radiation, kilowatts per meter squared, and this is the
time, so if you take the integral of the curve right
here, you're going to get what?
Units of?
Power times time is energy, energy per unit area, right?
So you're going to be able to calculate the total amount of
energy falling on a given area per day, let's say.
So if we look at the size of this little curve in winter, the
total area under this is going to be very small, that's because
the solar resource is very small, and the sun rises late and
sets early in winter.
And as we move towards summer, obviously the total amount of
the solar resource increases, not only it increases because of
this, that we have at solar noon, we have less of a path
through the atmosphere, we have more sunlight reaching
the earth, we have a total increase of the amount reaching
the earth, we also have that cosine theta term here dictating
the, say, the cross-section incident to that sunlight coming
in increasing, and so that's driving this going up, and we
also have a second fact that the time of the day, the total
duration of the day increases, at least in northern latitudes,
and here at around 40, let's say 41 degrees north, here in
Boston, and we have, because of these two effects, a much
larger area underneath that curve, and so as we go through
summer, and now finally to September 13th, and back to
winter, our solar resource goes back down again.
So you can calculate it, you can visualize it, that's cool,
and we can plot the total amount of energy per unit area per
day, essentially the integral under that curve, as a function
of location around the US, around the world, per month,
let's say, right, so this is January, this is kilowatt hours
per meter squared per day, so it's just taking the integral
of the curves measured, so it's accounting for cloudy days,
which kind of has a depressive effect, this is an envelope
function, if you will, the maximum you could get, and of
course local weather patterns will suppress that, drive it
down, so this is the real map of the United States, and you
can see in sunnier areas that are less cloudy, over here, for
example, in Arizona and New Mexico, there is a large solar
resource even in January, Atlanta, which has half of the
number of sunny days per year as Phoenix does, even if it's the
same latitude, is getting about half the solar resource, they
got a short end of the stick, again, this curve right here is
the envelope function, right, and off of that, you can only go
down, you can only decrease the amount of solar resource
actually arriving at our feet here, and so this is in January,
and this is all in the same color scale here, as we move
through the months, so we'll move from January to February to
March, April, May, June, July, August, September, October,
November, December, so you can see across the United States how
the resource is distributed geographically, the general
trend that as you go from south to north, you have a decreasing
solar resource holds, you can also see the influence of local
weather patterns as well for the same latitude, so that's pretty
nifty, and another nifty fact, if you look at the year average
value, annual, this is the annual average value, here in
Boston, we're averaging around 4.5 kilowatt hours per meter
squared per day, Phoenix, Arizona can be upwards of six
somewhere in the outskirts, it's not that bad, it's only a few
tens of percent, it's not that bad, I tell myself, I don't
believe it myself either, but I try to convince myself of that
during winter.
All right, let me show you the seasonal and urinal variations
from, we're increasing the level of sophistication as we go
along, we've assumed you've done your readings, we've started
with some simple examples, and now we're really taking it one
step further, which is to introduce the full 3D model,
and I'm going to do that by use of this really cool app that's
available here, right here, this is you standing on the earth,
and you can drag and pull us around, you can see this north,
south, east and west, so I'm going to pull it up a little bit
just to give us a little bit of perspective, still south is
facing toward us, north is away, the sun will rise in the east
and set in the west, now if I, let's say I pull the date back
to September, so this little tool is so cool because it
recognizes your IP address and situates you at the proper
latitude, so we don't have to touch that at all, it's
approximately right, we're at about 41 degrees, we're right
here in September, and in terms of time of day, we can pretty
much just cycle through the time of day if we like, we could,
for example, start animation, let's see, this is going very
fast right now, I'm going to slow it down, so you can see the
time of day moving right over here, and you can see this,
the relative to our vintage point on the surface of the
earth, this little yellow dot here and this yellow line is
tracing through the path of the sun and the sky, from our
perspective, and so as we go through the seasons, I'm going
to speed it up just a little bit so that we pay more attention
to the position of this yellow line and less attention to the
journal variations, we're paying more attention to the
seasonal variations, I'm going to vary the seasons by force
here, I'm going to go back to July or June, I may, here we go.
Yeah, so there's a number of other lines right here, and
they're all explained very carefully, there's the hour of
ascension, which would be, prime hour circle, yeah, so I
believe, I'd have to go back and double check all of this, but
I believe they relate to the, what would be the sunrise and
sunset of that given day, let's see if our hypothesis is
correct, no, it is not, that would have to be, since it's
varying in a systematic way from January, through the summer
and then back to the winter, I'm imagining this has something
to do with the direction of the sun, relative to the earth,
right, as it traces that ellipse through the sky. So let's pay
attention to that yellow line for a minute, that's the one I
want to attract everybody's attention to. Now we're in June,
so in the height of summer, and relative to this observer right
here, the sun is further up in the sky, just like we traced
out right there. And now as we go to winter, that line drops
closer to the horizon. So a couple of things happen, if we
look like this, for instance, now we're looking straight down
on the observer. In wintertime, the sun will rise in the
southeast, and it will trace this arc through the sky and set
in the southwest over here. In the summertime, the sun will
rise almost in the northeast, north of east, just slightly
north of east. And that's why if you have a north facing
window and you put your little plant on the windowsill, it'll
get a little bit of direct sunlight early in the morning
and late at night, is when the sun is tracing this part or
that part through, it's tracing the sky. So it's worth
sitting down with one of these plots, toying around with it,
getting accustomed to it, and understanding really how the
sun traces this arc throughout the sky relative to our
position right here on the earth. If we shift this further up
north, really interesting things begin to happen. So for
example, my wife is from Sweden. If we go to her hometown
right here, in the middle of summertime, right at the
solstice, you can see the sun traces this awesome route from
north to north, barely leaving the horizon. If we look at
again, from the perspective of the little creature here, that
that yellow arc is really close to the horizon. Maybe it goes
up about that high, but it continues going all the way to
the north. And if you keep going north, it will never set
during the middle of summer, it'll just be light all the
time. And you can see here, it just traces that orbit right
around there. It's all trig folks, we can do it, we can sit
down and we can work through the equations by hand. I did that
once, took me a long time, I didn't learn that much. I
would, I would instead advise you to go to one of these
simulations right here, but to understand all the inputs into
it, all the different components, right, the fact that the
sun, the earth is moving around the sun as a declination
angle, seasonal variations and so forth. Very useful tool, you
have the website link right here. And, and yeah. So from this
tool, actually, one last tiny, tiny thing, from this tool
right here, we can understand why, okay, this isn't, this is
real stretch and forgive me, social scientists in the room
for doing this, but I have to project a little bit of science
onto human behavior. How far west is Madrid from GMT? Madrid,
Spain. It's three degrees west of the, of the Great Meridian,
right? So the line that divides the east and the west
hemisphere is three degrees west. But it is one time zone
earlier than London, right? So it's in the same time zone as
Germany and all the other cities that are east of London. And
this is just for convenience factor. If you're traveling from
one continental European country to the other, it just makes
sense to have everything be on the same time zone, you get to
work at the same time, sort of pick up the phone, call somebody
you're doing business. Now, relative to everybody else in
Europe, though, is the sun setting later or earlier? If
you're that far west in your time zone? Later, right? So the
sun is setting later, if you're there. So if you're eating,
according to the sun, not according to what your watch
is saying, but if you're if you're choosing to eat dinner,
when the sun is setting, when will your watch say, Oh, my
goodness, it's really late. When you're in Berlin or when
you're in Madrid, when you're in Madrid, right? So again, I'm
not saying that this is the sole reason for social behavior
being a little different on the beer in peninsula, since
Portugal also eats very late in there in the same time zone as
London. But it could be a contributing factor, right? The
sun is still up in the sky when it's 5pm in winter, let's say,
and we're in Germany, it's set long time ago. So these are just
little things to keep in mind an easy way to calculate that an
easy way to calculate that when is the solar noon, you look at
the earth more or less like we're looking at this right now,
we have 360 degrees, we divide that into in the 24 time zones.
And then we say, Okay, about 15 degrees each, right? And then
we can begin counting from there. If in Boston, we're 41
degrees north, but we're 71 degrees west, right, we can say,
Okay, we should be for GMT minus five, we should be at around
75 degrees. And so we're a little earlier. So we do things a
little earlier around here than what the solar noon should be
telling us to do things. Wake up a little earlier, go to bed a
little earlier. And that's why students like, you're like,
Dang, there's no nightlife around here. Not saying that's
the only reason, but it could be a contributing factor. Whereas
the opposite happens when you're far west in your time zone.
Okay, so again, just trying to wrap our heads around the solar
resource and around the world around us so that we can answer
that little child in the shopping mall when they come with
questions. What are these?
Solar trash compactors, right? At the Student Center, Anastasia
is right over there. Duncan Donuts is there, right? So these
are solar panels mounted on the tops of those. And what the
solar is doing is charging a battery inside. Once the trash
reaches a critical level, sensors triggered, it stops you
from opening this bin, and it compacts the trash, right, and
then releases and allows you to open and put more stuff in. And
what it does is it minimizes the number of times between trash
pickups. If labor is a large portion of the cost of trash
management of waste of refuse management, then it eliminates
some of the labor, transferring it instead to the technology. And
so installing these at the Student Center, I had a little bit
of a pet peeve. So you have the angle of the sun right here,
which we just walked through 18 degrees in summer. And it just
so happened to work out that, and these numbers were
approximate, this was me going with my kind of engineering
sense, that's about 45 degrees, count the number of paces,
equilateral triangle, estimate the height of there. But in the
middle of summertime, when you are at the solstice, there is no
direct sunlight hitting this trash can because of that
overhang way up there. That's not a problem for this particular
trash collector, since those panels are way oversized for the
amount of energy that the trash collector actually needs. And
there is a fair amount of what we call diffuse sunlight, meaning
sunlight being scattered off of other things. That's why this
portion of the image looks white. It wouldn't look white if
there was no diffuse scattered black pitch black, if there was
no nothing to scatter the light off, like an outer space,
there's nothing to scatter. That's why it looks like a black
night. But instead, there's a large amount of diffuse light,
there is still some sunlight reaching it. And since the
panels are way oversized, and the system is over engineered, it
still manages to acquire enough energy to compact the trash, and
it doesn't have a catastrophic stop. But it was an example of
somebody not really thinking much about the direction or the
angle of the sun in the sky, they probably installed it
sometime around March, right when the snow started to melt, and
the sun was right around here. Right. And so you were the angle
was around there, and it made it into the trash collectors, but
you know, as the summer came along, it got shaded. So it's
something to keep in mind when doing a solar installation, it
is important to calculate these things. And I just pick out one
small example. I'd encourage you to walk through I was going to
have that be a small little in class example. But since we're
running short on time, I'll just give it to you like that. Okay,
fixed versus tracking systems. So if the sun is moving as a
function of season and as a function of time of day, throughout
the sky, and we can see that very nicely, again, to our demo
right here. So if the sun is actually moving, one embodiment
would say, Okay, I know more or less what the sun is going to
do as a function of season, forget that the urinal
variations, but just a seasonal variations. I know that the sun
is going to be on average somewhere around here, somewhere
around my latitude. So if I point my panel at latitude tilt,
right, since this angle was what was it, 41 plus 23, this
angle is 41 minus 23. So this one be right around 41 latitude.
So if I aim my solar panels at latitude tilt, then I'm going to
get, on average, some pretty decent power throughout the
year. I'll have a little less in winter, a little more in
summer, because well, just because of the amount of solar
resources available. But I'll be I'll be all right. At most, I'll
be off by 23 and a half degrees. You can do that. And that's
called fixed latitude tilt. And typically, you'll face the
panels south approximately. We'll get to that in a minute.
Depends on local weather patterns. If you have fog in the
morning, for instance, you want to face them a little to the
west. But but we'll face them south and a latitude tilt. Or we
can decide, no, let's actually track the sun throughout the
sky throughout the day. And so we'll start in the east in the
morning and have it rotating through on one axis tracker
throughout the day, or we can have a two axis tracker where it
rotates to follow the sun throughout the seasons as well,
kind of a north south tilt. And that's what's plotted right
here. This is a quick, a quick approximation of the fixed one
axis and two axis trackers for a given system in Boston, using a
simulation tool called PV Watts. There's a link to that. It's
based on the National Renewable Energy Laboratory website.
There's a link to that at the end of the slides. But this shows
you the total system output in terms of kilowatt hours, in
terms of hours per day. I think, yeah, it's a little bit of an
odd units there in the y axis, but it shows you the the
relative gain that you would get by going to a one axis and
then finally a two axis tracker. So in many places, it makes
sense to go to a one axis tracker, since especially you
broaden out the peak near the peak hours of the day, and
that's that's really good. But not always does it make sense
financially to go to two axis tracker, you're adding another
motor onto that thing, it's really not gaining you that
much. Obviously, you have to calculate it out yourself for
that specific location. But by and large, a generality, one
axis tracker makes sense for a flat panel. Now, if you have a
concentrator lens in the front, and it has to be looking
directly at the sun, then you're kind of forced to go to two
axis tracker. Okay, and there you have your total system output,
which is just the integral under the curve over the entire
year. So definitions should have done this before, but direct
sunlight looking directly at the sun and then diffuse sunlight
or scattered light coming off of other things, right? So the
few sunlight would be coming from the other angles in other
directions in the sky. The direct sunlight would pretty much be
at the sun, plus or minus a few degrees. And we have different
ways of measuring the, the, this would be flat plate up there on
the upper left is this flat plate facing south latitude tilt,
just like we said, it's facing south in the United States,
that's good. Latitude tilt, meaning it's tilted at our
latitude. So if we go from the southern tip of Florida and
Texas up to the northern tip of Minnesota, we'll be tilting it
more and more toward the south like this going from Texas to
Minnesota, right from Texas to Minnesota. And so latitude tilt
facing south flat plate. This is essentially accumulating all of
the sunlight, the direct and the scattered light, because it's
all being collected by that flat plate there. This map, on the
other hand, is for a two axis tracker. And it's looking at the
sun plus or minus two and a half degrees. And so it's really
only picking up this right here out of the sky. And when it's
sunny all the time, you're golden, you're tracking the sun,
you're actually getting more energy than you would if you just
had a flat plate, because the cosine theta angle is changing
throughout the day if you have a flat plate. When the sun is in
the morning time, you have a flat plate like this. So if my
sunlight is coming in like this, and I do cosine theta of the
angle, I'm only getting very small amount of the incident
sunlight projected onto this plate right here. Whereas in the
middle of the day, now cosine theta is one, I get the full
sunlight. But if I have, for instance, a tracker, I would be
able to face this panel, do east and then track it throughout
the day. And that's where I'd get this additional energy boost
here in the mornings, right, right there, from the tracking
system. So if I have a tracker, I get a big gain in the places
that have a lot of direct sun. And if I'm only looking at a
very small solid angle of the sky, if I'm only looking at say
this little portion of the sun, on cloudy days, most of the
sunlight is coming off of the diffuse light, not from the sun.
If I have a flat plate, I win. If I have a concentrator, I lose
on a cloudy day. And so that's why in some of the regions of
the United States that are notoriously cloudy, I won't point
to anyone in particular, it's actually better for non
concentrating solar in terms of total energy output. And in
other regions of the United States, where we have a lot of
sunny days, you start having two axis trackers making sense.
And it's just really the ratio of these two maps. This one,
which is flat plate, and that one, which is concentrator, you
see over here, we win if we go for the concentrator. And over
here, we get more energy out, oopsie, more energy out if we
use the flat plate. Now that's just energy. Obviously costs
and economics factors in what it what it takes to install it.
Okay. And weather patterns, I promise I'd get back to this.
Interesting to note that right near the equator, we have this
drop of the installation. And there are these beautiful maps
put out by again, by this NASA Earth Observatory that show you
the cloud fraction coverage of particular spots around the
planet. And you can see that right near the equator, is
typically we have these beautiful tropical forests. And
those are obviously the high cloud cover in those regions is
blocking out some of the sun. And likewise, you can see that
dichotomy between Phoenix and Atlanta, same latitude again,
but Atlanta having a higher cloud coverage than Phoenix and
hence, a lower solar resource, a lower installation. So you see
all this kind of ties together. That's all predictable, in a
sense. This is unpredictable, at a local level, at for one
system, right? If the sun is tracing its route through the
sky, and you have that envelope function, that you've just
spent so much effort calculating out with all your trig
functions, and the computer simulation, the code that you've
just been given here. And now a cloud comes over some random
cloud that was very hard to predict. And you just have one
panel, one tiny little thing like this, and the cloud goes
over it, boom, all of a sudden, you get a drop in your
instantaneous power output. Boom, drops again, another cloud
drops again, and then a thunderstorm in the afternoon. So
a meteorologist could have told you that this thunderstorm was
coming. But meteorologists would be hard pressed to be able to
predict the evolution of a tiny little cloud over your system.
And so the question is, to what degree are these weather, these
local weather patterns predictable and unpredictable? And
hopefully, some of you over this class will be able to help
answer that question by analyzing data from tens of
thousands of systems that have been installed throughout
California, in local geographical system, for example, in
Los Angeles region, San Francisco region, and so forth. If
you start averaging the curves, the energy outputs as a
function of time from a variety of systems throughout a
neighborhood, you can probably average out the small tiny
clouds. You probably can't average out the thunderstorm. But
you probably could have predicted that the thunderstorm
would have come along, right? And so this is a hot area of
solar research at the systems level is trying to understand
to what degree are PV systems predictable? To what degree can
the power output of a PV system, or an ensemble of PV systems
be predicted in advance? So we don't wind up in a situation
where all of a sudden we have this catastrophic drop of
accumulative PV system output of say 30%. And meanwhile, it's a
hot summer day, everybody's air conditions are going, and we
cause failure of the power grid, kind of worst case scenario.
So this boils down to intermittency with a short time
constants tend to be less predictable, cloud cover, and it's
relevant for predicting power supply reliability. And the
longer time constants tend to be more predictable, the journal
or seasonal variations. And these are relevant to calculating
total energy energy output annually. And oftentimes, when
we just work off of these long time constant variability
issues, we're assuming we have access to easy storage. Right
now, the solar panels on top of my roof, they're producing in
excess of what we're consuming right now, because neither my
wife or at home, and they're injecting that power into the
grid and the grid is serving as our big battery, as our storage
unit. And I'm riding free, I'm a free rider right now, I don't
pay for that service necessarily, I do the end star. But
they're not charging me extra for the service of, of, of using
the grid as my big battery. Another thing to keep in mind is
that we're calculating all of this on the basis of, of
engineering and scientific principles, we're calculating
the solar resource, which is a good important first step. Now,
if we look at the actual solar installations by year and by
country, this is a big table, but follow me on the two
underlined red lines here, DEU that stands for Deutschland,
Germany, and USA. We'll see that Germany has about seven times
more solar installed cumulatively than the United States
does. And yet, if we look at the solar resource in Germany,
relative to the US, this is average annual, same scale,
going from 900 to 1200 kilowatt hours per kilowatt per year, we
can see that there's a lot more sun in the United States than
there is in Germany. So there's something else going on than
just the solar resource. And that's the economics. That's why
we talk about the policy and economics later on in class.
That's why we dedicate a sizable portion later on talking
about that. Lastly, our final learning objective before we halt
for questions and for comments, we need to estimate the land
area needed to provide sufficient solar resource for a
project. And this is really where your homework picks up and
we'll spend some time in recitation walking through
this. But it's important to get your units right. And so I
want to do a quick quiz right now. Think in your minds, which
of these properties corresponds to which units are described by
which units over here on the right. So do kind of a linkage
in your mind, one to one, connect, connect, connect,
connect without looking at your slides. And we'll do it in three,
two, one. Those are your answers, right? So the ones that
usually get confused are power and energy, kilowatts and
kilowatt hours. The way to remember it, the easiest way
to remember it would be to remember that the power time
product is equal to energy. So if you have power, instantaneous
energy burn rate versus time, some plot that looks like this,
if you take the integral of that curve, that's your total
energy. So in terms of units, current voltage, power and
energy, a hairdryer versus a fridge, which is more likely to
blow a fuse and which is more likely to blow your budget?
Hair dryer is more likely to blow a fuse. Why is that?
High voltage.
Yeah, high voltage. Well, high current, really, because
everything's running 120. It's a higher current. It's pushing
the wattage up to around 1500, 1700 watts. And so it's running
close to the 15 amp limit. And the fridge, on the other hand,
is probably in order of magnitude lower. But the fridge is
running all the time, and your hairdryer is only running a few
minutes a day. So in terms of blowing a fuse, it uses a large
amount of power for a very short amount of time, whereas the
fridge uses a smaller amount of power for a longer amount of
time. And the integral under that curve winds up being more
typically than your hairdryer. That's the total amount of
energy. And you pay by the energy, you pay by the kilowatt
hour to your utility company. And that's why it would blow your
budget. Yep, oopsie. So the numbers work out to somewhere
around one kilowatt hour per day for the fridge and about half a
kilowatt hour a day for the hairdryer. A kilowatt hour is
how much in here? 18 cents? Most people pay about 18 cents per
kilowatt hour. And so you can calculate how much it costs to
keep things running in your house. Most of us don't usually
think about that. And last, last, last, last point, in your
homework assignments, you're going to be asked to size out
systems, PV systems, photo will take systems in different parts
of the world. And the easiest way to do that is if we take a
panel, and we say that this panel right here is rated at a
certain amount of power, right? So under peak illumination
conditions, when the panel is seated at incident sunlight, so
the cosine theta term is one. And the solar the incident solar
resource is 1000 watts per square meter. So around and 1.5
conditions. This panel right here would be producing this one's
time, I'll be producing on six watts peak. But most of these
panels over here are producing somewhere around a few hundred
watts peak. And so the panels are rated in terms of what peak?
Because the panel manufacturer doesn't know where you're going
to install them. You can decide that you're going to install it
in Alaska, in which case it's going to produce about half the
energy that if you install it down south in the continental US
and say Arizona, maybe a third of the energy. And so it doesn't
want to rate the panel in terms of the energy output, it's not
going to guarantee that you're going to get a certain energy
output off of the panel. But it'll guarantee that the panel was
rated at a maximum power of such and such under standard
testing conditions. Now that's good because you can generalize
it, which you'll do for your homework. But also as a downside,
because standard testing conditions aren't real world
conditions, the panel isn't always operating at 25 degrees
Celsius. The panel isn't operating always at incident
sunlight normal, right? And so the gap between actually knowing
how much the panel is going to output in terms of its energy
for a specific location and what our calculations, the back of
the envelope calculations will give us, that gap is from an
economics point of view, there's a lot of money to be made
there. If you understand really well how much a given panel
will output, you can then predict to a much finer degree what
you should be charging your customer for installing panels
in a particular location. So there's a lot of work being done
right now more on the business side of pulling the systems
engineers along and trying to increase the accuracy of
predictions. And so with that, I will, I will leave off on this
slide, we can get to it during recitation tomorrow at four. I
welcome your questions here at the front if you have any,
otherwise, I'll see you tomorrow.